They built the city to see what makes us tick. Last night, one of us went off.
Dark City is a mystery, science fiction film directed by Alex Proyas.
A man struggles with memories of his past, including a wife he cannot remember, in a nightmarish world
with no sun and run by beings with telekinetic powers who seek the souls of humans.
John Murdoch, played by Rufus Sewell.
Inspector Frank Bumstead, played by William Hurt.
Dr. Daniel P. Schreber, played by Kiefer Sutherland.
Emma Murdoch, played by Jennifer Connelly.
Mr. Hand, played by Richard O'Brien.
Mr. Book, played by Ian Richardson.
Dark City is a 1998 neo-noir science fiction film directed,
co-written, and co-produced by Alex Proyas.
It stars Rufus Sewell, William Hurt, Kiefer Sutherland, Jennifer
Connelly, Richard O'Brien, and Ian Richardson.
The screenplay was written by Proyas, Lem Dobbs, and David S.
In the film, Sewell plays an amnesiac man who, finding himself suspected of murder, attempts to discover his true
identity and clear his name while on the run from the police and a mysterious group known as the "Strangers".
Primarily shot at Fox Studios Australia, the film was jointly produced by New Line Cinema and Proyas's
production company Mystery Clock Cinema, and distributed by the former for theatrical release.
It premiered in the United States on 27 February 1998 and received
generally positive critiques, but was a box-office bomb.
Roger Ebert, in particular, supported the film, appreciating its art direction, set design, cinematography, special
effects, and imagination, and even recorded an audio commentary for the film's home video release.
The film was nominated for the Hugo Award for Best
Dramatic Presentation and six Saturn Awards.
Some critics later noted Dark City's similarities to and influence on the Matrix film series, whose first
installment came out a year later, and the film is now widely considered a sci-fi cult classic.
Concerned that audiences would not understand the film, New Line asked Proyas to
add an explanatory voice-over to the introduction, and he complied.
When a director's cut of the film was released in 2008, among the
changes was the removal of the opening narration.
The film explores themes of beach, experiment, paranoia, dystopia, sleep.
The tone is mind_bending and dark and thought_provoking.